Fokin Alexander

CONTACT Information Current Location: Los Angeles, United States

Mobile: +1 818 9198548 E-mail: apfokin@gmail.com

Personal Statement I strive for excellence in everything that I do. Software development is my passion, and I take great enjoyment in creating software that has a positive impact on the lives of others.

I stand out from my peers, even in highly competitive environments. I was in top 1% at the university, and currently I'm the most knowledgeable C++/Qt expert at Network Optix.

I perform well under pressure. At Network Optix I have almost single-handedly implemented the first version of the client application in a very limited time, basically making it possible to release the software before an important trade show.

I'll be happy to join a team of similarly self-motivated and highly competent professionals in a company with ambitious and far-reaching goals.

Professional Experience

Network Optix, Inc.

Senior Software Engineer

October 2011 - present

I'm currently working on HD Witness, an Enterprise Video Management System (VMS).

For the initial release I have almost single-handedly implemented the client application which was very well received in the industry. Various sources have described HD Witness as the most visually appealing and user-friendly VMS on the market, which has helped the company to gain a competitive edge.

Currently my main responsibilities include ensuring UI and UX performance and consistency of our desktop and mobile clients, management of the front-end development team, design of public APIs and development of generic C++ libraries that are used internally.

Combild

Software Development Lead, Co-founder

June 2010 - December 2011

Combild was started to create a program complex for IT infrastructure management that would target small companies and IT outsourcers. At the time all other solutions on the market were either too bulky and hard to maintain, or were not suitable for the business model of IT outsourcers. Frustrated with the state of things, we have decided to roll out our own product.

At Combild I have laid out the initial product architecture, was working with customers to prioritize and clarify the features and was managing a small development team.

Select LTD

Software Engineer

July 2009 - September 2011

At Select LTD I was mainly working on SmartDec, a native code decompiler. I have laid out the architecture of the decompiler and have implemented several frontend and backend plugins, including support for different x86 and PIC assembly input formats. I was also responsible for devising novel algorithms that would improve the quality of the decompiled code and would allow for reconstruction of C++-specific constructs. This effort has lead to several publications on international conferences on reverse engineering. Detailed description of the decompiler is available at http://decompilation.info.

As one of the side projects at Select LTD I have implemented a form recognition toolkit that was subsequently used in some of the Moscow schools for test checking. I have also participated in the development of business processes and supporting infrastructure for this project. Detailed description is available at http://elric.ru/wordpress/projects/form-recognition-toolkit/.

I was also doing some work on http://mathege.ru, a portal for national mathematics exam in Russia. I did both frontend and backend development and have implemented a IATEX to html converter that was used for importing problems into the system.

Institute for System Programming of the Russian Academy of Sciences

Software Engineer

September 2007 - September 2008

At ISPRAS I was working in a team developing a framework for dynamic analysis of binary code. Using C++ metaprogramming techniques I have implemented a disassembler for MIPS64 architecture that significantly outperformed all other disassemblers for this architecture known to our team.

Intel Research Lab at the Moscow State University

Software Engineer

February 2007 - April 2008

At Intel Lab I was learning computer vision algorithms and have implemented a panorama stitching application. Description is available at https://code.google.com/p/prec/.

As a side project I have implemented Ruby bindings for Intel's Integrated Performance Primitives library. Description is available at https://code.google.com/p/ipp4r/.

Personal Projects

I am an avid programmer and I enjoy writing code in my free time. Throughout the years I have done a lot freelance work and have finished several personal projects. For more information check out my google code page (https://code.google.com/u/100177180062339664882/) and my personal website (http://elric.ru/wordpress/projects).

EDUCATION

Faculty of Computational Mathematics and Cybernetics, Moscow State University, Moscow, Russia

Specialist degree in Applied Mathematics and Computer Science September 2004 - July 2009

Advisor: Professor Chernov Alexander

Thesis: Reconstruction of Class Hierarchies for Decompilation of C++ Programs

I have graduated with high honors. Diploma GPA is 5.0 out of 5.0.

Graduate School of Science and Engineering, Chuo University, Tokyo, Japan

Full-time non-degree student

September 2008 - March 2009

Advisor: Professor Mitsunori Makino

I was studying Japanese, working on algorithms for real-time ray tracing and have implemented a real-time ray tracer for use with CAVE automatic virtual environment.

Publications

A. Fokin, E. Derevenetc, A. Chernov and K. Troshina. "SmartDec: Approaching C++ Decompilation", in proceedings of the 18th Working Conference on Reverse Engineering, pp. 347-356, 2011.

A. Fokin, K. Troshina and A. Chernov. "Reconstruction of Class Hierarchies for Decompilation of C++ Programs", in proceedings of the 14th European Conference on Software Maintenance and Reengineering, pp. 249-252, 2010.

K. Troshina, A. Chernov and A. Fokin. "Profile-Based Type Reconstruction for Decompilation", in proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Program Comprehension, pp. 263-267, 2009.

HONOURS, TOEFL iBT, 111/120, Moscow, 2010.

AWARDS AND TEST SCORES M.V. Lomonosov Scholarship for Academic Excellence, Moscow, 2006-2009.

8th Moscow Collegiate Programming Contest, 9th place, Moscow, 2006. 7th Moscow Collegiate Programming Contest, 11th place, Moscow, 2005.

Unified State Exam in Mathematics, 100/100 (nationwide top), Izhevsk, 2004.

Related Experience managing a small development team.

Skills Substantial experience with C++ and Java.

Deep understanding of the underlying principles of modern C++ libraries and frameworks such as

Qt and boost.

A lot of experience writing cross-platform C++ code.

Considerable experience with multithreading in C++ and Java. Knowledge of modern realtime rendering techniques and APIs. Experience with Delphi, x86 Assembly, Linux shell scripting, SQL.

Some experience with C#, Matlab, Perl and Python.

Languages Russian: native

English: fluent

Japanese: intermediate

References Available upon request.